Today's דף daf *daf* is קל״ז *Kuf Lamed Zayin* 137 and we
pick up on קל״ו עמוד ב׳ *Kuf Lamed Vav Amud Bet* near
the bottom at
about I don't know twenty lines from the bottom at the two
dots: חומר בזרוע ולחיים ובקיבה *Chomer ba’zroa u’lchayayim u’va’keiva* with the two
dots and the bracket וכולי *v’chulei*. Okay, so the משנה Mishna, *mishnah*
mentioned ways in which זרוע ולחיים ובקיבה *zroa u’lchayayim u’va’keiva* has a
broader stroke than the ראשית הגז reshit hagez? *Reshis HaGez*, the most
obvious being of course that ראשית הגז reshit hagez, *Reshis HaGez* only
applies to sheep and only five of them. But now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says that there are more things that could have been
included. So let's take a look. וליתני חומר בראשית הגז שנוהג בטרפות
מה שאין כן במתנות *v’litni chomer b’Reshis HaGez she’noheg b’trefos mah she’ein
kein b’matanos*. How about the fact that ראשית הגז reshit hagez *Reshis
HaGez* applies to טרפות *trefos*, right? Why and why should it matter?
But it doesn't apply by מתנות matanot *matanos*. Why doesn't it apply
by מתנות matanot *matanos*? So I would have thought that the reason
it doesn't apply by מתנות Matanos *matanos* is because it says זובחי
הזבח *zovchei ha’zevach* and it's a שחיטה שאינה ראויה *shechitah she’eina reu’uyah*.
And remember there's a whole debate whether a שחיטה *shechitah* that does
not make the animal permissible to eat is considered a שחיטה *shechitah*.
רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says, he says I don't know if it's a
דרשה drasha *drasha* somewhere but רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says ונתן לכהן *v’nasan
la’Kohen*, you should give it to the כהן Kohen, *Kohen* so it'll
be for him to eat, not for his dog to eat, and
if it's a טרפה *trefa* he can't eat it. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* takes for granted that it doesn't apply to טרפה *trefa*.
טרפה אינה בכלל מתנות matanot *trefa einah bi’khlal matanos*. So anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so why didn't we list it? So
אמר רבינא Ravina הא מני רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon היא *Amar Ravina
Ha mani Rabbi Shimon hi*. It's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*.
דתניא detanya, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon פוטר את הטרפות מראשית הגז *D’tanya
Rabbi Shimon poter es ha’trefos mi’Reshis HaGez*. Not to challenge the question
of that by מתנות *matanos*, but to say maybe the same is
true by ראשית הגז reshit hagez *Reshis HaGez* that a טרפה *trefa*
is also not, you don't give, if you know it's a טרפה
*trefa* obviously. So מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון *Mai ta’ama d’Rabbi Shimon*? What's
the reasoning of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*? ילפינן נתינה נתינה
ממתנות *Yalfinan nesina nesina mi’matanos*. We make the link to the gifts
of the זרוע ולחיים ובקיבה *zroa u’lchayayim u’va’keiva*. מה מתנות טרפה לא
אף ראשית הגז reshit hagez נמי טרפה לא *Mah matanos trefa lo
af Reshis HaGez nami trefa lo*. The same way by the gifts
not, which we're taking for granted. רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says as we
said, רש״י *Rashi* says it's because of ונתן *v’nasan*. So the same
by ראשית הגז reshit hagez *Reshis HaGez*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
one minute, ויליף נתינה נתינה ממתנות לילף נתינה נתינה מתרומה *v’yalif nesina
nesina mi’matanos leilaf nesina nesina mi’terumah*. This is like echoing yesterday or
two days ago. Once you're making a link, why not link it
to תרומה terumah *terumah*? מה תרומה terumah. בארץ אין בחוץ לארץ לא
אף ראשית הגז reshit hagez נמי בארץ אין בחוץ לארץ לא *Mah
terumah ba’aretz in b’chutz la’aretz lo af Reshis HaGez nami ba’aretz in
b’chutz la’aretz lo*. Which we know was רבי Rebbe, אלעזר׳ס *Rabbi Elazar's*
position but not the position of the משנה Mishna *mishnah*. If you
really are willing to make, use this word to link it to
other things, link it to תרומה *terumah* and then limit it to
ישראל *Yisrael*, which we know is not the case. אלא תנן *Ela
tnan* why does our משנה Mishna *mishnah* teach ראשית הגז reshit hagez
נוהג בארץ ובחוץ לארץ *Reshis HaGez noheg ba’aretz u’v’chutz la’aretz*? It applies
in the land of Israel and outside? אלא *Ela*, you're right. Forget
it. Let's not get into that whole business again about linking it
to other things. So that's not how come we exclude we exclude
a טרפה *trefa* from ראשית הגז reshit hagez. *Reshis HaGez*. אלא *Ela*,
so why is it excluded because it wasn't listed in the משנה
Mishna *mishnah* as a point of difference? אלא היינו טעמא דרבי שמעון
*Ela hainu ta’ama d’Rabbi Shimon*. This is the reasoning of רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon*. It's funny that we're still linking it to,
I'm sorry, no, because we have the ברייתא braita *baraita* that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* exempts. So here's the reasoning of רבי
Rebbe שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. דיליף צאן tzon, צאן ממעשר *D’yalif tzon tzon
mi’ma’aser*. מה מעשר maaser. טרפה לא אף ראשית הגז Reishis Hagez טרפה
לא *Mah ma’aser trefa lo af Reshis HaGez trefa lo*. Not ונתן
*v’nasan* which puts us in the תרומה *terumah* category, but a linking
with the word מעשר maaser *ma’aser*. I mean a word צאן *tzon*,
excuse me. Both this is sheep and מעשר maaser. *ma’aser* is used
as the phrase sheep: you give the tenth of your newly born
sheep. And in the same way by מעשר maaser *ma’aser* you don't
give a טרפה *trefa*, here too you do not give a טרפה
*trefa*. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says והתם מנלן *v’hasam minalan*? How
do you know there that's true? I mean we know obviously you
can't bring a קרבן korban. *korban* as a טרפה *trefa*. But how
do you know you don't sanctify it as מעשר maaser *ma’aser* and
then have to redeem it? Because actually if the tenth animal that
walks out of the pen has a מום Mum, *mum*, has a
blemish, it does get sanctified and
then it's eaten with its מום *mum*. I mean not redeemed, it's
eaten with its מום *mum*. So maybe you should say the same
by a טרפה *trefa*? How do you know a טרפה *trefa* does
not become מעשר maaser. *ma’aser*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says דכתיב
*d’chtiv*, the verse says כל אשר יעבור תחת השבט *kol asher ya’avor
sachas ha’shavet*, anything that passes under the rod when you're counting them
for the tenth, which as I said includes even something with a
blemish, but how do I know it excludes a טרפה *trefa*? פרט
לטרפה שאינה עוברת *Prat l’trefa she’eina overes*, because a טרפה *trefa* can't
walk under the rod. Now why can't it walk under the rod?
Because there are some טרפות *trefos* that actually is a טרפה *trefa*
because let's say it's missing a leg. So therefore it excludes טרפה
*trefa*. Now that bothers תוספות *Tosafot*, because תוספות *Tosafot* says first of
all, you know, there are some things that aren't טרפות *trefos* that
also can't walk, like if it has a if the lower leg
is broken is is broken,
you know the hoof is torn off, it's not a טרפה *trefa*
and it also can't walk under. Are you also going to say
that that's exempt? So it's a little bit of a funny that
we focus on this quality of being able to walk under the
staff which is and then exclude a whole category of טרפה *trefa*
and not just the literal case of when it doesn't have the
ability to walk under. But that's how the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* makes
its דרשה drasha, *drasha*. And since therefore מעשר maaser. *ma’aser* does not
apply to an animal that's a טרפה *trefa*, according to רבי Rebbe
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* it does also not apply for ראשית הגז Reishis
Hagez *Reshis HaGez* and that's why it was not mentioned in the
משנה Mishna. *mishnah*. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ולילף
צאן צאן מבכור *v’leilaf tzon tzon mi’bechor*? You think you're going to
get out of it by using צאן *tzon* and not ונתן *v’nasan*
so that you can't I don't know link it out from anywhere
else, but no it says the word sheep or flock by the
firstborn, and there we know it does apply by a טרפה *trefa*
because the firstborn is just automatically
sanctified by the fact by virtue of it being born. מה בכור
bechor, אפילו טרפה אף ראשית הגז Reishis Hagez, אפילו טרפה *Mah bechor
afilu trefa af Reshis HaGez afilu trefa*. So why not say the
same way a בכור bechor applies of an animal applies to a
טריפה, treifa, the same is true of ראשית הגז? Reishis Hagez מסתברא
ממעשר הוה ליה למילף. mistabra mimaser hava lei l'milaf. No, it's better
to learn it out from מעשר. maaser. Why? And now we're going
to do one of those fun things where you can learn something
out from category A or category B, so you have to figure
out which has more points of connection or more relevant points of
connection. So now we are going to point out which is more
similar to ראשית הגז, Reishis Hagez the בכור, bechor which we know
we don't want to say because we don't want to learn from
בכור bechor one minute, or from מעשר maaser. which we are going
to learn from. We'll take your question in a minute. Let's take
a look at the way points that ראשית הגז reishit hageiz. is
connected to מעשר. maaser.
שכן זכרים, sheken zecharim, here sometimes these words mean that it shares
the fact that it's not that it doesn't have this. מעשר maaser
and ראשית הגז reishit hageiz are not limited to males, whereas בכור
bechor is limited to males. טמאים, tmeim, they do not apply to
non-kosher animals, whereas בכור bechor applies to a non-kosher animal, right? There's
a concept of בכור bechor by a donkey.
במרובים, bimrubim, it only applies if you have a lot of them.
ראשית הגז reishit hageiz. you need five sheep and מעשר maaser, you
need ten sheep, right? That's the tenth. Whereas בכור bechor applies even
to one. מרחם, merachem, neither of them are sanctified from the moment
they're born as opposed from the womb, as opposed to בכור bechor
that is sanctified from the womb. אדם, adam, neither of them apply
to humans, whereas בכור bechor, applies to humans. Most of these notice
are what they don't have and בכור bechor, does have, but okay.
פשוט, pashut, neither they both apply to non-firstborns. That's pretty relevant and
only to non-firstborns, because once an animal is a בכור, bechor. it's
not also sanctified as מעשר. maaser Once it's a בכור, bechor right,
the gifts, the ראשית הגז reishit hageiz does not apply to animals
with sanctity. So there is the exact sort of inverse of בכור.
bechor. בכור bechor only applies to firstborn, this only applies to non-firstborn,
non-בכור. bechor לפני הדיבור, lifnei hadibur, and neither of them were relevant
before the Torah was given at Har Sinai. That's what לפני הדיבור,
lifnei hadibur, before the speech, before the proclamation, you know, before God's
message to the Jewish people, whereas בכור bechor we know, you know,
that there was a concept even in Egypt about the special status
of בכור bechor and the בכור bechor, being chosen and so on.
Whatever, exactly. Okay. So that's why it has more points of connection
to מעשר. maaser. So the Gemara's not done. אדרבה! aderaba! מבכור הוה
ליה למילף! mibechor hava lei l'milaf! I'll show you that the gifts
from the ראשית הגז reishit hageiz are more similar to בכור bechor
than they are to מעשר. maaser How is that? שכן יתום, sheken
yatom, first of all they both apply to an animal that is
a orphan. The mother dies when the animal's being born. So you
might remember that one of the things that rabbis learn from שבעת
ימים יהיה תחת אמו, shivat yamim yihiyeh tachat imo, an animal seven
days with its mother and it could only be a sacrifice on
the eighth, it actually actually treat that literally and say that if
the mother dies while the animal's being born, it cannot be brought
as a קרבן. korban,
However, so that would apply to מעשר. maaser.
For seven days, right?
Presumably. Yeah, the classic example they give is that the mother dies.
Now that is true by מעשר. maaser. However, by ראשית הגז reishit
hageiz you don't need it to be a קרבן, korban, and by
בכור, bechor. בכור bechor, is the one category that's always an exception
because things are automatically sanctified from the womb. So therefore it does
not have these limitations. So therefore they both apply to an animal
that's an orphan.
שלקחו, shelakchu, they both apply to something that's purchased. An animal that
is purchased,
מעשר maaser is only the animals that were born in your flock.
If you buy a lot of young sheep, you don't give מעשר,
maaser. it's only animals that were born to you. Whereas if you
buy a lot of sheep and you shear them, you give ראשית
הגז. reishit hagez If you buy, you know, and if you buy
a sheep and it gives birth, you give בכור. bechor So it
applies even to something that was purchased.
בשותפות, beshutfut, okay, partnership.
So we,
one minute, one minute, I'm looking up- מעשר- Maaser back.
Now, it's- so although there was an opinion that מתנות are exempt
by partnership, right, that's not the position of our Mishnah, we don't
read it that way. So if you have a partnership with a
Jew, you give the מתנות and you give בכור, Bechor but interestingly
that does- that is an exception by מעשר. Maaser מעשר Maaser of
a בהמה behema is only when it's solely owned.
נתנו, netano, one minute,
oh, if it was given as a gift, which is similar to
the idea of שלקחו. shelakchu. So if you received it as a
gift, the animal, you would still give בכור Bechor once it gave
birth, you would give the shearings if you sheared it, but if
you received it as a gift, again it wasn't- it was purchased
by you, it wasn't born into your flock, you do not give
מעשר. Maaser So again that's a way that they are both dissimilar
from
מעשר. Maaser בפני כהן, bifnei kohen, and Rashi actually reads this two
ways. בפני, bifnei, they apply only when there is a בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, although Tosafot says really everything- I mean they- excuse me,
they apply even without a בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but the point
is that that's true- לי- li right, that would be בפני הבית,
bifnei habayit, whatever. Anyway, Tosafot doesn't like that because even מעשר Maaser
applies not in- when there's no בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, meaning you
can't bring the קרבן, Korban, but the animal is still sanctified as
מעשר. Maaser. So Tosafot switches the גירסא girsa to לפני, lifnei, which
he
means... לפני Lifnei means the הלכה Halacha by מעשר Maaser is if
you accidentally miscount and you count the ninth one as tenth or
the eleventh one as tenth, they also become sanctified. So מעשר Maaser
has the ability to pull with it the things that come before
and after it. Whereas בכור Bechor and ראשית הגז reishit hagez, is
only obviously the thing itself. Okay, כהן, Kohen so what's the idea?
כהן Kohen. is what? Hold on. Oh, you give it to the...
you give it to the כהן. Kohen, So you give the first
shearings to the כהן, Kohen, you give the בכור Bechor to the
כהן, Kohen. but מעשר Maaser, you eat yourself, you bring it as
a קרבן, but you don't give it to a כהן. Kohen Okay,
so you have all of those points. And, one minute, בקדושה, Bikdusha,
they, בכור Bechor,
you don't have to sanctify them. It's true בכור Bechor. has sanctity
and ראשית הגז Reishit Ha-geiz. does not, but neither of them do
you have to do an act of sanctifying as opposed to מעשר
you have to do an act of counting it the tenth, an
act of sanctifying it. Okay,
ומכירה. Umechira. Yeah, the act of shearings. Yeah, that's true, but it's
not the act that imparts sanctity. Okay, and מכירה Mechira which is,
which is... what?
You could say it's pre-designated. Right.
Okay, where you're allowed to sell, a כהן Kohen can sell a
בכור, Bechor? you know,
somebody else, to another כהן kohen let's say, he would eat it,
or sell it if it has a מום, you can obviously, he
can sell his ראשית הגז, Reishit Ha-geiz? but מעשר the Torah says
לא ימכר, Lo Yimacher, shall not be sold. So those two can
be sold and מעשר cannot be sold. So you have all of
these ways in which it's connected to בכור. Bechor, So why not
learn it off from בכור? Bechor. Again, if anybody forgot the context,
the question is whether how do we know whether ראשית הגז Reishit
Ha-geiz. applies by a טריפה? Treifa? So we say it doesn't apply
by a טריפה Treifa according to רבי Rebbi שמעון because we learn
it from מעשר. So it says, oh, but there's all these other
points of connection to בכור, Bechor. let's learn it to בכור. Bechor
So the והני נפישי V'hani Nifishei and those are even more, those
points of connection to בכור. Bechor So the גמרא Gemara says no,
פשוט מפשוט עדיף ליה. Pashut Mipashut Adif Lei. No, nevertheless, there was
a much... the strongest point of connection is that בכור Bechor. is
only בכור Bechor and not non-firstborns, and מעשר and ראשית הגז are
only non-בכור. Bechor, So that is a pretty big point difference, right?
בכור Bechor. its whole identity is בכור, Bechor. and these things' whole
identity is when they're not בכור. Bechor So therefore, their whole status.
So therefore, clearly you'd rather learn it out from מעשר than you
would learn it out from בכור. Bechor... So with that, ha, we
know that we learn out from מעשר, we know according to רבי
Rebbi שמעון it doesn't apply by a טריפה. Treifa. Yes.
This idea that בכור Bechor is קדוש Kadosh before הר סיני Har
Sinai is that like an implication from the exchange with the לויים
Levi'im or is there some other...
Yeah, I mean that's what רש"י Rashi says. Let me check what
רש"י Rashi says again. רש"י Rashi says,
where's רש"י? Rashi?
In the
middle.
קדשו במצרים Kadshu beMitzrayim רש"י Rashi says. Yeah, he doesn't actually... he
doesn't actually... that's the last narrow line. He doesn't actually mention... or
three lines...
פדיון בכורי ישראל. Pidyon Bechorei Yisrael.
Yeah, he doesn't... but he doesn't actually mention the לויים Levi'im because
the לויים Levi'im were not the בכור... Bechor oh, you mean by
the fact that you needed to do the פדיון Pidyon of the
לויים. Levi'im. Right, that could very well be. Or the fact, you
know, that already in מצרים... Mitzrayim... it's not clear. Does he also
mean כל בכור? Kol Bechor? That's what I mean. Does he mean
that there was a מצוה Mitzvah before הר סיני Har Sinai that
related to it? That would be the easiest thing to say. Meaning,
you know, that they actually had the halachic status, that you had
the מצוה Mitzvah פדיון בכור Pidyon Bechor and all that whole thing
was given in מצרים Mitzrayim before הר סיני. Har Sinai. Yeah, that
would be the easiest thing to say. But it's not so clear
that ובכורות קדשו במצרים, U'bechoros Kidshu beMitzrayim, he didn't say like נצטוו
ממצרים, Nistavu miMitzrayim, so I think there's some ambiguity in רש"י, Rashi,
you know, maybe because that... that רש"י Rashi I think more a
little bit echoes the whole idea of the פדיון Pidyon of the
לויים Levi'im that happens later. כי לי כל בכור, Ki Li Kol
Bechor, you know, and... well, actually that כי לי כל בכור Ki
Li Kol Bechor is by the ציווי. Tzivui. So I don't know.
There are multiple elements.
והנה V'hinei in שמות Shemos it's the לשון Lashon קדשת לי, Kadashta
Li, right? By the מכה. Makkah. So they were kind of... they're
קדוש Kadosh but in a strictly, you know, halachic sense the way
the גמרא Gemara wants to understand it, there's no מצוה Mitzvah to
do anything about it until הר סיני. Har Sinai. Right. But isn't
the מצוה...
Mitzvah... but the בכור of בהמה Beheima is there, right? In the...
yeah, that's what I'm talking about. Right, right, right. It doesn't say...
what does it say? It doesn't have the פדיון בכור? Pidyon Bechor?
It has the פדיון בכור Pidyon Bechor of the בכור of the
חמור, Chamor, right? So you actually have מצוות בכורות Mitzvos Bechoros there,
yeah, yeah. You had a question?
We were asking on רבי Rebbi שמעון from the משנה, Mishna but
we didn't want to say he holds like רבי אלעאי. Rabbi Elai.
Did we really not want to say anyone holds like רבי אלעאי?
Rabbi Elai?
Well we can't say the משנה Mishna is רבי אלעאי. Rabbi Elai.
Right, no, so we asked him, oh, the משנה Mishna says, he
said I disagree with the משנה Mishna, because I hold like רבי
אלעאי. Rabbi Elai.
No, but the... our question was about the משנה. Mishna. Why the
משנה Mishnah, didn't give טריפה Treifa as a point of difference? Why
give all these other things as a point...
No, we said about
אלמא תנן ראשית הגז נוהג בחוץ לארץ. Alman Tan Reishis Hagez Noheg
Bechutz La'aretz.
Yeah, we had to make the משנה Mishnah. רבי שמעון because we
wanted to say why טריפה Treifa wasn't a point of difference. But
the משנה Mishnah. also explicitly says it applies in חוץ לארץ. Chutz
La'aretz. It's a point about how we're explaining the משנה, Mishnah not
how we're explaining רבי שמעון. We're using רבי שמעון to explain the
משנה. Mishnah All right, so now let's continue. Top of
קל"ז עמוד א'. Kuf Lamed Zayin Amud Aleph. ראשית הגז אינו נוהג
אלא ברחלים. Reishis Hagez Ein Noheg Ela Berachelim. So here, it only
applies by sheep as opposed to the מתנות that apply by cattle
and sheep and goats. Okay, but this only applies to sheep. So
מנא הני מילי? Minan Hani Mili? Where do you get this from?
אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda אתיא גזי גזי. Atya Giza Giza.
You make a גזירה שווה *gezeirah shavah*, shearing shearing. כתיב הכא ראשית
גז gez, צאנך *K'tiv hacha reishit gez tzonecha*, the shearing of your
flock, and תתן לו *titen
lo*, וכתיב התם *v'k'tiv hatam*, meaning the question is how do we
know not to include goats? Now if you look at תוספות *Tosafot*,
why would I have thought to include goats? So תוספות *Tosafot* quotes
a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* where the word צאן *tzone* is used by
goats, right? Look at the תוספות *Tosafot*, מנא הני מילי *mana hani
mili*, תוספות *Tosafot* says לך נא *lech na*, just the second line
of תוספות *Tosafot* where it says בראשית כ"ז *Bereishit Kaf Zayin*, לך
נא אל הצאן וקח לי משם שני גדיי עזים *lech na el
hatzone v'kach li misham shenei g'deiyei izim*. Right, so there you go.
By רבקה *Rivka* and יצחק *Yitzchak*... wait, רבקה *Rivka* and יעקב *Yaakov*,
right? She says go... no, yeah. Yeah. She says go to the
flock and take for me two goats. So you see goats could
be included in flock. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to know
how do you know that the flock, the shearing of the flock,
does not include goats? So it says we make a גזירה שווה
*gezeirah shavah*, גזא גזא *geiza geiza*, shearing shearing. כתיב הכא ראשית גז
צאנך תתן לו *K'tiv hacha reishit gez tzonecha titen lo*, וכתיב התם
ומגז כבשי יתחמם yitchamam *v'k'tiv hatam umigez k'vasai yitchamam*, and from the
shearing of my sheep and there it's כבש *keves*, which is sheep,
not goat, goat would be גדי *g'di*. My sheep you shall like
warm yourself. So there you see it uses גז *gez* specifically in
the context of sheep, although that of course is a פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* in איוב Iyov? *Iyov*. תוספות *Tosafot* says okay, it's not a
real גזירה שווה *gezeirah shavah*, but we learn out from there that
when we talk about shearing flock, we mean shearing sheep, not goats.
Also, goats you don't really shear anyway. But yeah, so מה להלן
כבשים *ma halla k'vasim*, the same way there it's sheep, אף כאן
כבשים *af kan k'vasim*, here too it's sheep. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says ונילף גזא גזא מבכור *v'neilaf geiza geiza mib'chor*, why not
learn shearing from the firstborn? Where does... what does that mean? דתניא
Detanya, *d'tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא baraita *braita*: לא תעבוד בבכור
שורך *lo ta'avod bivchor shorecha*, do not work the firstborn of your
cattle, ולא תגוז בכור צאנך *v'lo tagoz b'chor tzonecha*, and do not
shear the firstborn of your sheep. So אין לי אלא *ein li
ella*, the ברייתא baraita, *braita* says I only know שור בעבודה וצאן
בגיזה *shor b'avodah v'tzone b'geizah*. You can't work your ox and you
can't shear your sheep. מנין ליתן האמור של זה בזה והאמור של
זה בזה *minayin litten ha'amur shel zeh bazeh v'ha'amur shel zeh bazeh*,
how do I know to apply one to the other, that you
also can't work your sheep and shear your ox? תלמוד לומר Talmud
lomar, לא תעבוד ולא תגוז *Talmud lomar lo ta'avod v'lo tagoz*, neither
work nor shear. Somehow the fact that those two verbs are, I
don't know, they're not even juxtaposed but they're parallel, somehow we learn
to apply maybe the ו' *vav* to apply one to the other.
So you see, if we want, I mean it's very bizarre, I
mean does... do cows have much hair that you could use? What
could you use if you shaved a cow? I don't know. Anyway,
but you see we're prepared to say that the word גז *gez*
or shear would apply to what? Buffalo? Buffalo have hair?
Yeah, in the front.
Oh, okay, oh, ah, that's a good point. Okay, fine. All right,
so anyway, so we're prepared to apply the word גז *gez* to
cows, so maybe we should say the same true here even though
it says צאן *tzone*, maybe צאן *tzone* is לאו דווקא *lav davka*,
maybe it means anything that you shear and would include even the
case of let's say buffalo. So אמר קרא *amar kra* תתן לו
*titen lo* ולא לשקו *v'lo l'sako*. You should give it to him
and not for his sack. So you cannot use and as we
said before, the תתן לו *titen lo* means for some type of
clothing for him to use personally on his own body. So therefore
presumably from cow hair or buffalo hair, I guess you would not
make clothing. Somebody's going to tell me that the American Indians
did otherwise. What? Yak hair is used...
Yak hair is used for sackcloth? For sacks? For clothing.
Ah, a קשיא *kashya*. All right, I don't know.
Anyway, so תתן לו *titen lo* meaning clothing anyway,
לו *lo* personally, his body,
as opposed to like his use?
Yeah. That's how we're דרשנינג *darshening* it. So אלא מעתה *ela ma'ata*,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says נוצה של עזים לחייב *notza shel izim
l'chayev*, okay, but how about goat hair? Now again, the question is
seems to be you wanted to make your link to this verse
about sheep, but since we know that in other cases by, for
example, the בכור *bechor*, you know, which also applies to goats, right,
we know that the idea of shearing is used more generally. So
why so... so maybe you can't limit it to sheep. And now
even though you said that it would not work for cattle, at
least maybe it should work for goats.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, בעינן גיזה giza וליכא *ba'inan
geizah v'leika*, you have to be an act of actually shearing and
you don't shear when you come to remove the hair from... you
actually pluck individually the hairs? Wow.
That's what said in the Artscroll?
That's what it says, I mean I'm not...
All right, I don't know. It's got to be highly inefficient. I
gotta imagine you did something other than plucking, but maybe you used
a razor, I don't know. I imagine it was something that was
not called shearing. But to pluck each individual goat hair?
They said they had something that plucked a lot of hairs.
Oh, maybe. Gotta be very painful for the goat. All right, anyway.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says now, מאן שמע ליה
האי סברא *man shama lei hai sevara*, who have we heard says
this idea that is very precise with the scope of the word,
that if the word says shearing it means only a shearing? רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi. *Rebbe Yosi*. We're going to see רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi *Rebbe Yosi*, we're going to see it in like two lines
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So one minute, הא מודה רבי יוסי
במידי דאורחיה Modeh Rabbi Yose bimidi de'orchei. *ha modeh Rebbe Yosi b'midi
d'orchei*, even if רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Rebbe Yosi* interprets the verb
in the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in its narrow meaning, he only excludes
doing something that would be unusual, but if something that's not the
norm, but if... Here, the plucking or whatever you do of the
goat hair is the normal way you remove the goat hair. So
that's not excluded by the verb גיזה. giza, גיזה giza is shearing
would exclude let's say plucking sheep hair. Doing something that was the
same removing, but doing it in an unusual way, not through an
act of shearing. But it would not exclude plucking goat hair which
is the normal way of removing goat hair. So this is a
very strange, it says even though the Torah uses the word גיזה,
that would not be sufficient and even if you precisely define the
word, that would not be sufficient to exclude the analogous case of
removing hair from a goat in the normal way. So how do
we know to exclude that? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא כדרב
יהושע בן לוי, ela k'derav Yehoshua ben Levi, לעמוד לשרת, la'amod l'shareit,
that it says that this is God has given the כהן kohen,
who's to stand to serve, you know, in the temple, it says
that in this context of the ראשית הגז. So the גמרא Gemara
says, דבר הראוי לשירות, davar harauy l'shirut, you have to be able
to make from this something he could use as a בגדי כהונה.
bigdei kehuna. So if it was wool, wool could be used in
the בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, but goat hair was never used in
the בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, so that is not included. So הכא
נמי, hacha nami, דבר הראוי לשירות. davar harauy l'shirut. So the same
way he's going to say that in tomorrow's דף to tell us
something about the amount and the quantity using this model of could
be go towards a בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, here too we use
the same thing to tell us what type of material, and therefore
only wool, not anything else, goat hair would not be possible to
use. So we're using this sense, now we've done that twice, that
this is something that he has to use personally, a garment, and
it could even potentially be a בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna to tell
us not other materials but only something that is wool. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara, says, אלא גיזה גיזה למה אתא? ela giza
giza lama ata? What's the point then of linking the two words
of גיזה to this verse about warming yourself in איוב? Iyov, Now
again, it's a very strange question because that wasn't a real גזירה
שוה, gezeira shava, it was a פסוק pasuk in איוב, but nevertheless,
now that we've introduced that verse that says you warm yourself with
the shearing of sheep and we have another way of learning out
the idea that this מצוה mitzvah applies only to sheep and only
to wool, what do you do with that verse? So the גמרא
Gemara says, לחדתני דבי רבי ישמעאל, l'chadtani d'bei Rabbi Yishmael, like what
they taught in the house of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. דתנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל, d'tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael, they taught in the house of
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, כבשים שצמרן קשה פטורין מראשית הגז. k'vasim shetzamran
kasheh peturin me'reishit hageiz. Very interesting. If the wool is stiff and
hard and will not make good clothing, then you cannot you would
not be obligated to give towards ראשית הגז that type of wool.
שנאמר ומגז כבשי יתחמם. shene'emar umigeiz kvasai yitchamam. From my shearings you
shall warm yourself. So therefore it means that it has to be
able to make clothing that's soft enough that you know it wraps
around the body and it's good for warming, right? If something is
very stiff and it sort of does not you know shape itself
to the contours of the body, then it will not be good
for warming yourself. Now רש"י Rashi interestingly says on this
that it just means stiffer than the norm, that it's really more
of a relative category. I think רש"י Rashi says, let me just
find the רש"י. Rashi.
Yeah, where is that רש"י? Rashi?
Right
before it gets warm.
יתחמם right before the גמרא. Gemara לא מגז כבשי יתברכוני. lo migeiz
kvasai yitbarechuni. No.
שצמרן קשה. shetzamran kasheh. The one before it. כגון שהיו משונים משאר
כבשים. k'gon she'hayu meshunim mish'ar k'vasim. So I'm not sure if what
he means by that is, you know, is to say that the
way you determine it is a relative standard or he's just saying
no no no in an unusual case where, but it's still would
be defined by an objective standard that you don't warm it's not
good enough to give you any warmth. הרמב"ם Ha-Rambam just says the
latter. That it's a type of wool that would not be able
to give you warmth if turned into clothing. I mean, any layer
will give you warmth, but not in any serious way it won't
give you warmth and therefore it would be excluded.
Yeah, it would be like a stuffing for quilts.
Yeah, you could use it for something like that, but you would
not be obligated to give ראשית הגז. So again, it's quite interesting,
right, it's quite interesting the way we're specifically interpreting ראשית הגז to
be something that can translate into clothing. You know and it's interesting
also that the רמב"ם Rambam who usually does not indulge in sort
of agadatic discussions or sort of like meanings of מצוות mitzvot discussions,
except he leaves that to the very end of a הלכה, halacha,
you know like at the very end of הלכות שבת hilchot Shabbat
or particularly at the very very end of הלכות מועד hilchot moed
of one you know of the ספרים, sefarim, he'll give like a
הלכה halacha that speaks about some broader hashkafic point. But anyway when
he talks about ראשית הגז right in the middle he says, so
the Torah gave him grain from the תרומה and it gave him
meat from the קרבנות korbanot and from the מתנות and gives him
you know the ראשית הגז for his clothing. So it's very interesting
that he like introduces that right in the middle of his halachic
discussion and actually here we see that that has halachic significance, that
we're using it to exclude hard wool, we're learning it to using
it to learn that we only give wool, we're going to later
use it to learn how much wool we give him, it has
to be enough wool that he could make a small garment out
of. So the idea that this is headed directed towards clothing really
here shapes a lot, shapes a number of the הלכות. halachot. Okay,
so now we go on.
Okay, תני חדא גוזז את העזים ושטף את הרחלים פטור. tani chada
gozez et ha'izim v'shoteif et haracheilim patur. One ברייתא Baraita, says if
somebody shears here does use the word shears, shears goats, which we
know is exempt, that we've already established, but it also says...
You sort of rinse, there's got to be a better word, but
anyway the sheep, like the פסוק pasuk from שיר השירים, Shir Hashirim,
right, which it says, you know, what
does it say? כעדר הרחלים העולות מן הרחצה, ke'eder harechelim ha'olot min
harachtza, right, like you know, a flock of sheep they're coming out
of basically you would like pass them through a river, right, you'd
walk them through a river, hopefully they wouldn't get swept away whatever
or some stream, and through that, you know, they would that would
be a bath. Okay, now apparently what could happen in that process
is depending on the current or whatever, some of the wool could
get torn off from their body naturally through the stream. So if
enough wool gets torn off, do you have to give ראשית הגז
from that? Is that considered like you sheared them if it happened
sort of you know indirectly?
So you would have that wool in hand?
Yeah, let's say you would go and you would try to collect
it from the you know that why not? It's wool, who wants
to waste it?
And it's floating downstream.
So you catch it, maybe it's more of a pond than a
stream, I don't know whatever the case. Okay, so anyway, I don't
know how I don't know if it's so theoretical. Anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara
says like this,
yeah, exactly. You can't shear a sheep anyway unless you bathe it
because then the wool mats and collects dust and collects dirt and
becomes like...
right, so this was maybe immediately prior, right, this might be right
immediately prior to the process of shearing it and you want to
make sure you collect everything.
All right.
That was by the way shed as opposed to shear, like dogs
shed, I shed. I see. The shedding process so it's not even
clear that you plucked, I'm thinking like brushing or something like that
as opposed to...
Ah, that makes more sense. I can't imagine that you really pluck
by goats. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, yes,
also there was about goats, the first de-hairing, so they must have
been plucking. Machine was invented by a guy by the name of
Dawson in 1890. Plucking machine.
Good to know. So how did they do it before that? Plucking.
Right, how did they do it before that?
Without the machine.
I'm working on it.
Okay. Focus. All right. שקט בבקשה. sheket bevakasha. All right.
So since he created the machine, it's most probably that they did
it by hand.
Well yeah, but maybe they did it by hand by brushing rather
than plucking. That's the question. Anyway, all right, let's take a look.
So one says that those are exempt, that's not considered an act
of shearing, and the other,
ותניא אידך, vetanya idach, but a different ברייתא braita, says, הגוזז את
העיזים פטור, hagozez et ha'izim patur, it's true that the goat hair
is exempt, but והשוטף את הרחלים חייב, vehashoteif et harechelim chayav, by
the bathing of the sheep, if that tears off wool you're obligated.
So how do you explain that? So the גמרא Gemara says, לא
קשיא, lo kashya, הא רבנן והא רבי יוסי, ha rabanan veha Rabbi
Yosi, it's the debate of the רבנן rabanan and רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yosi. The question is do we interpret the word גז, shearing, in
its narrow sense and therefore only an act of shearing, or do
we interpret it more abstractly as any process that removes the wool?
Okay, and that's the רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
we've discussed.
Your purpose of your
intent?
Presumably, or maybe yeah, it might also be
in terms of the species differences in terms of the fact that
sheep don't shed. Right. You have to actually do an act of
removal, like you have to pluck the hair off from the body
in order to
separate it, whereas goats shed, the hair's already removed, you just have
to gather and collect it.
Right, right, but also going to Michael's point, as I thought you
were going to say your other point, if it's really true that
you would do this רחיצה rechitza right prior to the shearing, then
I'm not so sure, and you know it's going to result that
some hair's going to fall off and you're doing the process, right,
so that might
be a... meaning meaning... no, I don't know, but anyway, we might
not just be talking that it fell off, this is a process
that you are doing that you are aware of this as a
consequence. So that's... this is the רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi we discussed
before, how narrowly you interpret the verb to shear. So let's take
a look. So הא רבנן והא רבי יוסי, ha rabanan veha Rabbi
Yosi, one is the רבנן, rabanan, one is רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is of the position generally says we interpret
these verbs more narrowly and literally and not abstractly. דתניא, we taught
in a ברייתא, Baraita לקט קצירך, leket ketzircha, now not having to
do with ראשית הגז, another discussion about the droppings when you are
collecting the wheat, anything that slips through your fingers and that you
drop you leave to the poor. So it says the droppings of
your harvesting, of your scything, I guess, is that what it's called
a scythe? Scything? I'm trying to turn that into a verb, scything
or something, anyway, ולא לקט קיטוף. velo leket kituf. If you just
plucked or were plucking wheat and something dropped, you would not have
to leave it as לקט, leket, because even though that's your... because
it's a strange way of removing it and therefore it's not included
in the verse and it's not literally the קציר, katzir, the harvest.
רבי יוסי אומר אין לקט אלא הבא מחמת קציר. Rabbi Yosi omer
ein leket ela haba machamat katzir. לקט leket is only something that
comes as a result of, you know, using your scythe and of
harvesting and not something that is, we're going to say, not something
plucking. So the גמרא Gemara says, רבי יוסי היינו תנא קמא, Rabbi
Yosi hainu tana kama, isn't that exactly what we just said? כולי
רבי יוסי, kuli Rabbi Yosi, you're right, it's not two opinions, this
is really just רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is explaining the תנא קמא,
tana kama, it's all רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose. opinion. והכי קתני, vehachi
katani, and here's how it reads, שרבי יוסי אומר, sheRabbi Yosi omer,
because רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose was of the opinion, was of the
opinion... is of the opinion, אין לקט אלא הבא מחמת קציר. ein
leket ela haba machamat katzir. Okay, so now רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says that we read the verb narrowly, not abstractly, and even though
it produces the same result, if it's not the normal type of
the process, so the wool coming off the sheep is not the
normal way of doing the process, you are not... you are not
obligated, literally it has to be shearing.
So the גמרא Gemara says... even if...
comes off by the wash.
But as long as you intended it, right?
Ah, that's not clear. How abstractly they would interpret the verb is
not clear. Right, so I made it a little more palatable by
describing it that way. But we don't know the exact extent of
how abstractly they would go.
By the way, you don't like stand there with like your basket
and try to gather the shearings from the that are floating downstream
in order to give them?
No, no, no. No, I mean if you don't have it, you
don't have enough, no. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, alright,
so, אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי. Amar lei Rav
Acha brei deRava leRav Ashi. So רב אחא בריה דרבא Rav Acha
brei deRava said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, מודה רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose במידי דאורחיה. This is what we said before. He doesn't limit
it completely to the literal meaning of the verse. If you had
another process that was that was directly analogous, wasn't exactly that act,
but it was the normal way of doing it, then he would
agree. He's only excluding like plucking wheat, like you know, the river
pulling off wool. That's not the normal way of doing things. But
if it was analogous and it was by a different object and
it was normal to do it that way, then he would agree
that that's included. דתניא, we taught in a ברייתא, רבי יוסי אומר,
Rabbi Yose omer, קציר כתיב. katzir ketiv. אין לי אלא קציר. Ein
li ela katzir. I only know harvesting. עוקר מניין? Oker minayin? How
about uprooting? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, לקצור, liktzor, to harvest, this is
all again by the פסוקים pesukim about the about the droppings, about
the לקט. leket. תולש מניין? Tolesh minayin? How do I know about
plucking off? תלמוד לומר, בקוצרך, b'kotzrecha, in your harvesting. So these extra
words of harvest, harvest, harvest are other types of harvest. So what
does that mean? So it means when this is the norm, like
how do I know about pulling up onions? How do I know
about pluck picking off tomatoes? So since that that would be included,
says רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose Not plucking wheat, but plucking tomatoes and
pulling up and pulling up carrots, that is included in the verb.
Okay, so there you see that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is not
is not totally literal, but he limits it to cases that are
directly analogous, normal ways of doing it, not abstractly anything that produces
the same result. Okay, so אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amar lei
Ravina leRav Ashi, said רבינא to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, אף אנן
נמי תנינא, Af anan nami tanina, we also taught in the משנה,
Mishnah, excuse me, מלבנות בצלים שבין הירק. malbinot betzalim shebein hayerek. So
basically in terms of פאה, pe'ah, the only things the only vegetables
obligated in פאה pe'ah were onions and and garlic because one of
the qualities of פאה pe'ah the גמרא Gemara understands is that it
has to be something that you store, and those are the only
like vegetables that are put away for storage, others are have to
be eaten fresh. So therefore, what if you basically had a field
that alternated between, I don't know, rows of carrots and rows of
of onions? So, I don't know, we're not learning פאה pe'ah now.
So, would you have to give one פאה pe'ah for each row?
Is each row separate because it's separated by a row of carrots
which is not obligated in פאה? pe'ah? Or do you still look
at the whole field as a unit and say there are onions
in this field, I'll give one פאה pe'ah for all of the
onions in the field? So that's the debate in the משנה. Mishnah,
מלבנות בצלים שבין הירק, malbinot betzalim shebein hayerek, they're between rows of
one minute vegetables. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose omer, פאה מכל אחת
ואחת, pe'ah mikol achat ve'achat, you give פאה pe'ah on each row
of onions. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, מאחת על הכל, me'achat al hakol,
one on all. Now why is this relevant? Because we're not concerned
about one פאה pe'ah or multiple פאה, pe'ahs, we're concerned about the
fact that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says you give פאה pe'ah on
onions. So why? It's not קצירך. katzirecha. The תורה Torah uses the
same פסוק pasuk of קצירך katzirecha by לקט leket and by פאה.
pe'ah. The פסוקים pesukim we just quoted were were those פסוקים. pesukim.
So you don't you don't harvest onions like with a scythe. So
you see that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi, says that if it's the
normal way of doing it, you know, uprooting onions, plucking off tomatoes,
that would also be included. Okay, so there we have an interesting
position of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi which the גמרא is taking not
only by לקט, leket, but assuming it as a more general position,
which is how narrowly or abstractly do you read certain verbs. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi, reads it, you know, not totally literally, but only
something that is the the very classic way of doing it, whereas
perhaps the רבנן Rabbanan are prepared to read it sometimes more abstractly.
The question how abstract, how broad is not clear. Did you have
something you wanted to contribute, Bobby? Okay. So now we go on
to the next line in the משנה. Mishnah And this gets a
little complicated, which is what is the number two questions: how much
wool do you need to be obligated, and then how much do
you give? Okay, and with how much do you give, there are
two ways of measuring it. One is what proportion of the wool,
maybe it's a proportional measurement, and the other is is there a
minimum amount? So we're going to first start with the question of
how much do you need to be obligated. Okay, so if you
remember there בית הלל's Beit Hillel the first opinion was besides number
of sheep, how much comes from each sheep? So the position was
מנה מנה ופרס, mane mane u'pras, one and a half מנה, mane,
where was it?
וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, that was the position of דוסתאי בן הורקנוס,
Dosetai ben Hurkanos, and the חכמים Chachamim say כלשהו. kolshehu. No, even
if the sheep only produce five sheep, but even if they only
produce a tiny amount. Okay, so let's take a look. Right? There's
right, how much sheep, how much wool, and then how do you
give, and give defined proportionally and defined by a minimum. But we're
first going to discuss how much wool now that we've decided you
need five sheep. Okay, but oh actually, I'm sorry, I jumped ahead.
First we're going to decide whether you need five sheep or not.
There's the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit
Shammai how many sheep. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says... two sheep and
בית הלל Beis Hillel says five. So first let's figure out how
many sheep, then we'll figure out how much wool. Okay, so בשלמא
לבית שמאי תרתי נמי קצון. Bishlamah le-Beis Shammai tarti nami katzon. So
בית שמאי Beis Shammai quoted a פסוק pasuk where two are called
sheep. So fine, five are called sheep but two are called sheep.
That's not a problem, but two are also called a flock, I
should say not sheep, a flock. אלא לבית הלל מאי טעמא? Ela
le-Beis Hillel mai taama? So wonderful, בית הלל Beis Hillel quoted a
פסוק pasuk that said five of the flock, but there's also a
פסוק pasuk that said two. How do you ignore the פסוק pasuk.
that says two? How do you say the minimum is five? So
אמר רב כהנא אמר קרא, Amar Rav Kahana amar kra, the verse
says: עשויות. asuyot. Because the verse that בית הלל Beis Hillel quoted
it says five sheep that are laden or are made. What does
it mean made? So עשויות שעושות, asuyot she-osot, it's in the plural
that they do שתי מצות. shtei mitzvot. It means that they allow
you to do two מצות mitzvot if you've got five sheep. What
מצות mitzvot do they allow you to do? ראשית הגז ומתנות, Reishit
ha-geiz u-matanot, that you can give the gift when you שחט shecht
them to the כהן, kohen? the זרוע ולחיים וקיבה, zeroa le-chayayim ve-keivah,
you give the shearings. So therefore since it used the word עשויות
asuyot by five, we learn that it means that they help you
do two מצות, mitzvot, and therefore now they're helping you do and
therefore that's when they become obligated in ראשית הגז. So the גמרא
says: אימא בכורה ומתנות? eima bechorah u-matanot? How do you know it's
ראשית הגז? Maybe the two things that you can give from those
sheep are the firstborn and the gift to the כהן? kohen So
the גמרא says: בכורה חדא מי לא מיחייבא? bechorah chada mi lo
michayva? Says no, then you wouldn't have needed five, then it would
have been then even with one you could give the gifts to
the כהן kohen. and the firstborn. So the גמרא says: ולטעמיך מתנות
חדא מי לא מיחייבא? u-letameich matanot chada mi lo michayva? Okay, says
the גמרא, but clearly you don't need five for both of the
מצות mitzvot you're saying the פסוק pasuk is talking about, you don't
need five for the זרוע ולחיים וקיבה. zeroa le-chayayim ve-keivah. So once
the five is not relevant for both of the ideas, maybe it's
not relevant for either of them. Maybe that's not what the פסוק
pasuk means. So the גמרא says: אלא אמר רב אשי עשויות, ela
amar Rav Ashi asuyot, let's try again. עשויות asuyot means שמעשות את
בעליהן ואומרות לו קום עשה מצוה. she-ma'asot et ba'aleihem ve-omrot lo kum
asei mitzvah. Not in the plural, but in the sort of הפעיל
hif'il causative, that no, causative I think, that or that they forced
you know, they they they impose an action on their owner. עשויות
asuyot means they make their owner do something. Because there are five
of them now you gotta do something. What you gotta do? You
gotta do this מצוה mitzvah of ראשית הגז. So somehow we're making
the דרשה from the extra word of עשויות. asuyot. But still we
don't know that
that's not the same by two.
Well, the verse says five. So by five you get that, right?
It's saying why say five, why not say two, why not say
three? So you see only it only makes you do the מצוה
mitzvah when it's five. תניא דבי רבי ישמעאל. Tanya d'bei Rabbi Yishmael.
So that's two and five, בית הלל, Beis Hillel, בית שמאי. Beis
Shammai. Now we have another opinion. In the house of רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael we taught, רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosi omer, the son
of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi said, so or in the name of
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi's excuse me, not
son. בר רבי יוסי אומר משום אביו, Bar Rabbi Yosi omer mishum
aviv, the son of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi's says in the name
of his father, thank you, ארבע ארבע, arba arba, four sheep. שנאמר,
shene'emar, as it says, וארבע צאן תחת השה. ve-arba tzon tachat ha-seh.
He quotes a פסוק. Right? What happens when you steal something, you
know, steal a sheep and you and you sell it or you
slaughter it? You have to pay four sheep in replace for the
one you stole, stole. So there it uses the word צאן, a
flock, and it says four. So he says four, which is like
a middle position between בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis
Shammai somewhat middle. Okay so anyways, the גמרא says: תניא, tanya, now
we taught in a ברייתא, אמר רבי, amar Rebbe, said רבי, אלמלא
דבריהן דברי תורה, ilmalei divreihem divrei Torah, were the words of בית
הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai learned from פסוקים psukim
in the תורה, Torah, right? בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי
Beis Shammai learned it from פסוקים psukim in נ"ך, Nach, not פסוקים
psukim in the תורה. Torah. So he says like this, even were
בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai learning their position
from פסוקים psukim in the תורה, Torah, ודברי בי רבי קבלה, ve-divrei
bi-Rebbe kabbalah, and the words of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi's he used
the word בי רבי bi-Rebbe as an honorific, the words of רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi's were learned from words in from פסוקים psukim in
תנ"ך, Tanakh, אנן דברי בי רבי שומעין, anan divrei bi-Rebbe shomin, we
would have we would go by רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi's opinion. It
makes more sense. וכל שכן, ve-kol she-ken, how much more so now,
שדבריהן דברי קבלה, she-divreihem divrei kabbalah, that בית הלל Beis Hillel and
בית שמאי Beis Shammai are only learning from פסוקים psukim in נ"ך,
Nach, not פסוקים psukim in the תורה, Torah, ודברי בי רבי דברי
תורה, ve-divrei bi-Rebbe divrei Torah, and רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi, learning from
a פסוק in the תורה Torah where it says four by the
word of a flock, how much more so should we follow רבי
יוסי's Rabbi Yosi position? So רבי clearly likes רבי יוסי's position, certainly
because even more because he's learning it from a פסוק in the
תורה Torah and he says we go by four. Now the גמרא
wants to say, so one minute, if it's it sounds like he's
fundamentally liking it regardless of which verse he's learning it from. So
what does he like about רבי יוסי's position? So the גמרא thinks
well maybe what he likes about it is that it's a compromise
position, right? That it's somewhere between the extreme of בית הלל Beis
Hillel and בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, maybe that's what attracts him to
that position. So the גמרא says that can't
be, והאמר מר אין הכרעה שלישית מכרעת, ve-ha'amar Mar ein hachra'ah shelishit
machra'at, a not a what's it? Yeah no no, how do you
say הכרעה? hachra'ah? It's like when you weigh in favor of a
particular position, you know, so a but a weighing in favor, if
it's a third opinion, does not is not considered tipping the scales.
It's got to be a yeah a word anyway is not considered
a is not considered a significance.
Yeah, thank you. I'm stumbling over my words. Let me sort of
reframe it, okay, the following way. Normally, if you have two positions
that stake out like the way רבי like like one position says
this law applies whether it's case A or case B. And the
other position says this law doesn't apply whether it's Case A or
Case B. And then you have a middle position that says you
know what, it applies in Case A, it doesn't apply in Case
B. That's called a דעת מכריע, Da'at Machria, an opinion that actually
tips the scales in favor of a middle position. Why? The way
רש״י frames it is the following: because when I say it applies
in Case A, then it's two against one regarding Case A, because
the first opinion said it applied in A and B. When I
say it doesn't apply in Case B, it's two against one that
it doesn't apply in Case B, because the other position said it
doesn't apply in A and B. So I've sort of split my
vote, half with this, half with that, and therefore I win because
I have in every of my position, I have somebody else, each
half of my position, I have somebody else that sides with me.
That's considered a דעת מכריע. Da'at Machria. And there we say you
go by the דעת מכריע Da'at Machria when it is a middle
position. But that is different than what's a דעת שלישית. Da'at Shlishit.
דעת שלישית Da'at Shlishit means these other opinions didn't even think that
A and B mattered. They just, one said it applied, one said
it didn't apply. I introduced a new idea. Oh, I've got a
great compromise. Let's say it applies in A and not in B.
As far as they're concerned, A and B are not even relevant
categories. So therefore that's really a completely third opinion, even if it
situates me in a continuum halfway between the two opinions, it's not
logically sort of splitting the vote. It's really just a third opinion.
There's still two against one.
No, this time I would say two, three, and four.
I understand. Anyway, so this is the point that we do not
necessarily, it doesn't mean my opinion is invalid, but it means we
don't necessarily rule by it. It's a compromise position, it is not
a sort of like splitting of a vote. If I split my
vote, half in one case, half in the other, then I'm going
to help each side for half and that's going to be the
way we're going to go. But if I don't split my vote,
I just sort of have a middle road position, then it doesn't
have any more weight than any of the others. What?
Why didn't they just see what people were doing? These
are early.
That's a good question. I mean, I imagine, right, but why isn't
that a question by any rabbinic debate? You know, I mean, presumably
we're talking in a time where there's a lot of diversity of
practice. You know, I mean, heck, we even learned in חולין Chullin
that in the place of רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yose HaGlili they
would have, you know, they would have chicken and milk, right? There's
a lot of diversity in practice even amongst the Jews that are
following the rabbinic leadership. There were plenty of Jews at that time
that were not, you know, that were not following rabbinic leadership.
So, you know, and they were trying to systematize, codify, unify the
practice. So, I don't think you can ever say let's just see
what people are doing. I mean later sometimes you would say like
when we said נהגו עלמא Nahagu Alma k-whatever, sometimes there does develop
somebody, but very often we're dealing with a wide diversity of practice.
Yeah.
Back to goats. Goats, yeah. The Sumerians removed hair with
tweezers, white vine or ivy gum extracts, asses' fat, she-goats' gall, bats'
blood, and powdered viper. Wow. No doubt Middle Easterners used a hair
removal process called body sugaring in those times.
Okay, so there you go. So not all by plucking. Plucking was
probably the least efficient. Some by what do they call it, depilatory?
Why would you take a tweezer and pluck?
I know, I'm just saying that was one of the ways, but
that's got to be the least efficient of them. Okay, anyway, so
how do you determine the difference? That's a good question. So you
could say sort of logically, you know, do you see this position
as sort of logically,
you know, not just bottom line middle, you know, halfway between, but
sort of logically, you know, combining halves of each position. רש״י says
it's also a question of how the two extremes articulated their positions.
If this guy says, if this, excuse me, תנא Tanna says or
whatever, you know, in both cases A and B it's חייב. Chayav.
And this says neither A or B it's חייב. Chayav. They're both
acknowledging that there could be a reason to distinguish between A and
B. They're just denying that that's true, but they acknowledge that those
are relevant categories. So there if you say A yes, B no,
you are, you know, playing within, having the same conversation as they
are. As opposed to if they're not even acknowledging those differences. That's
the way רש״י explains it. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא says, so
the reason רבי likes it can't be because it's a middle position
because it's not. It's not logically halfway. He's not saying in some
cases two and in some cases five. He's saying four. So it's
a middle position, but it's not a tipping position. It's not a
מכרעת. Machra'at. So אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rebbi Yochanan, no, here's why
he liked it. מפי השמועה אמרה, Mipi HaShemuah Amrah, because he had
it from tradition. מפי חגי זכריה ומלאכי, Mipi Chaggai Zechariah U'Malachi, from
the last of the נביאים. Nevi'im. I have no idea how רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan knew that. How did he know that he had
it from tradition and בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit
Shammai didn't have it from tradition? And if he had it from
tradition, that he had it from חגי זכריה ומלאכי. Chaggai Zechariah U'Malachi.
So it's a very strange end to that discussion. Interestingly, the רמב״ם
Rambam rules and the גאונים Geonim rule like בית הלל, Beit Hillel,
five, not four. So even though רבי liked this position, right, in
the end they went by more normal types of principles of פסק,
Psak, which is you rule like בית הלל. Beit Hillel.
And for the tradition.
What? And for the tradition. Which gets to another important הלכתי halachic
point, which is that the גמרא that the משנה Mishnah says, it's
actually ironic, there's a משנה Mishnah. or a ברייתא that says that
you do not rule from a משנה, Mishnah which does which means
not only from a debate in a משנה, but even if in
the משנה says הלכה כדברי halacha kedivrei X, that's just the משנה's
opinion. But the actual ruling has to come through discussions that emerge
after the משנה. So even though רבי likes the position of רבי
יוסי, that does not end the story and the רמב"ם Rambam actually
rules five. Okay, so now we go on. Now we get to
the question not how many sheep, but how much wool and how
much you give. So first רבי יוסי בן חורקנוס אומר Rabbi Yosi
ben Horkenos omer etc. So רבי יוסי בן חורקנוס Rabbi Yosi ben
Horkenos says you need a מנה ופרס, maneh u'pras, one and a
half מנה. maneh. Again, I don't I should have before this figured
out the weight of this, which I didn't, but I will tell
you that the basic
what's it
called conversion chart is that a מנה maneh is 30 סלע. sela.
So a סלע sela was a certain size of a coin. You
can imagine, but it's like you know whatever, imagine it's like a
relatively I don't know, I'm guessing, some coin like about that big.
Okay, and a מנה maneh is 30 of them. So the first
opinion was you need one and a half מנה, maneh, 45 סלע
sela from each sheep in order to be obligated. So according to
בית שמאי Beis Shammai that would be the weight, that would be
225. רבי יוסי that's רבי יוסי בן חורקנוס, Rabbi Yosi ben Horkenos,
that's what he says. וחכמים Vachachamim say even a little bit, כל
שהוא. kol shehu. So of course the גמרא says וכמה כל שהוא?
vekamah kol shehu? How much is even a little bit? Okay, so
אמר רב amar Rav מנה ופרס. maneh u'pras. So he says the
same amount, one and a half מנה, maneh, but that's for all
five sheep combined, not from each sheep. ובלבד שיהיו מחומשות, Uvilvad sheyihyu
mechumashot, as long as it's equally divided amongst the five. So he
agrees that there has to be a minimum not just of total,
a minimum from each sheep, but it's exactly one-fifth of the previous
opinion. Okay, so it's one and a half מנה, maneh, so from
each sheep, which means each sheep produces a half of a מנה.
maneh. No, that's wrong, that would be two and a half, that
would be two and a half, excuse me. So anyway, each sheep
so it's a total of 45 divided by five, each sheep produces
nine סלע. sela. That's what he would say.
Which means if one of them produced nine and the others produced
nothing, you would not be obligated.
Clearly, but not only that, if five of them produced ten and
one of them produced eight, you would not be obligated. You need
each one to produce a minimum of nine. Okay, alright. So does
that tell you how much a סלע sela weighs? Probably not. Artscroll
doesn't like to commit to those things. Alright, anyway, alright, so that's
his opinion,
okay, one and a half for all five. ושמואל אמר, U'Shmuel amar,
שמואל Shmuel says שישים ונותן סלע אחת לכהן. shishim venoten sela achas
l'kohen. No, it has to produce 60, right, 60 סלע. sela. So
a מנה maneh is 30, so the first position said one and
a half total, which is 45. שמואל Shmuel is saying essentially two
מנה, maneh, 60, and he says you give one to the כהן.
kohen? So this now we're getting into not only how much minimum
do you need, but what do you give to the כהן? kohen,
And שמואל's Shmuel introducing the idea 1/60th, which is an idea that
we know by תרומה. Okay, so שמואל's Shmuel both saying the minimum
is 60 סלע sela and one goes to the כהן, you give
1/60th. And that actually might be, let me flip it, that might
be where he gets the number of 60 as the minimum amount
of wool. Since you give 1/60th and you have to give something
of significance, you start by the idea that the smallest you would
give is a סלע, sela, and therefore you get to the idea
that you need to start with 60. Is that clear? That you
might start by the end, you know you have to get to
a סלע, sela, so therefore if it's 1/60th, you know you need
to start with 60. רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Rabbah
bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar
bar Chana said in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, שש
לכהן. shesh l'kohen. No, שש. shesh. You can 6 is enough. You
don't need 60, 6 סלע, sela, 1/10th of what שמואל Shmuel said,
almost nothing. Okay, very tiny amount. One minute.
שש לכהן חמישה ואחד לו. shesh l'kohen chamishah ve'echad lo. But he
also disagrees with שמואל Shmuel on another point. שמואל Shmuel says you
determine what you give by a proportion, 1/60th. He says, if you
remember the משנה says, the minimum you give is five סלע. sela.
So because so he starts so שמואל Shmuel starts with forget there's
no bare minimum, it's a proportion, but well there is a bare
minimum, it's one סלע, sela, but the fundamental idea is a proportion,
so you get from one סלע sela you get back to 60.
That's how much you have to start with. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says no, no, no, the minimum you give is an absolute amount.
It is not a proportion, it is the base that you give
is five סלע. sela. So if it's five סלע, sela, how do
I know how much I have to start with? Well, what is
the smallest you would have to start with in order to give
five סלע? sela? Five. No, because we said ראשית שיהיו שיריה ניכרים,
reishis sheyihyu she'reha nikarim, right, at least that was one דרשה, you
need something left over. So if you have to give five, what's
the minimum you have to start with? Six. Six. Somebody's going to
say five plus epsilon, but let's talk in whole units. Okay, so
therefore רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says six. So it seems they're both
working with the end and working backwards. שמואל Shmuel is working with
a proportion, so if a סלע sela is the smallest unit, you
work backwards from a סלע sela and you get 60. And רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is starting with five as the absolute minimum that
you give, and therefore you work backwards you get six. That's רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
According to שמואל, Shmuel, it's a proportion, so if you shear 600,
yeah, then you'd give 10.
Right. שמואל's Shmuel position, which
שמואל's Shmuel makes a little bit more sense,
right,
but maybe not
at
all.
approximately eight pounds.
For one סלע? sela? It can't be one סלע. sela. No, no,
no, for the מנה mana and פרס. pras.
No, no, it's combined.
For which? For the one of מנה mana and פרס?
pras? Each fleece of sheep weighs at least 1.5 מנה, mana, which
is the equivalent of 37.5
silver סלעים. selaim. Right, for total shearing from the five sheep of
187.5 סלעים selaim or approximately eight
pounds.
For the entire, for the position of, of the first position of
five times one and a half.
So, okay, wait a minute, where's he getting 37 and a half?
I thought you said it was only nine סלע sela for the
minimum.
No, no, he's saying seven and a half, right? They were starting
with seven and a half. They were starting with a position of
what, of רב? Rav?
This is בית הלל's Beit Hillel position.
בית הלל, Beit Hillel,
דוסא בן הרכינס.
Dosa
ben Harkinas. No, no, no, I'm just saying the number they started
with there was seven and a half. When they started with seven
and a half and they started doing their whole math, what was
the first number they started with?
One and a half מנה, mana, she said.
The minimum number is five.
Oh, the מנה mana is 100 דינר dinar according
to this.
How does a דינר dinar relate to a סלע? sela?
There are, there are, well, a מנה mana is 100 דינר dinar
and there are 30 סלע sela in a מנה, mana, so three
and a third, I guess, דינר dinar to a סלע. sela.
Okay.
I have a question. Yes. We're assuming they all agree on five
sheep?
Right. Any difference between the number of sheep they're counting for a
flock?
One minute, hold on, am I doing the math right? Hold on,
I'm just, give me a second.
Why do I think I just got that wrong? One minute, hold
on a second.
Oh, I'm sorry, I've been saying 30, but that's wrong. I don't
know why I was saying 30. In the end of the גמרא
it says 40. Maybe I was just trying to make the math
easier. Okay, I thought, I'm sorry, because right, because actually, exactly as
you said, the סלע sela to the דינר dinar is a much
more, is a much more easy math. Right. Okay, everybody erase, take
back. I mean, the basic point I said about all the positions
was correct, but in terms of the conversion table, I'm sorry, I
got confused. The conversion actually is, right, there's 100 דינר dinar to
a מנה, mana, and there's four דינר dinar to a, I'm sorry,
100 דינר dinar to a מנה, mana, there's four דינר dinar to
a סלע, sela, there's 25 סלע sela to a מנה. mana. Right,
I'm sorry, I got that wrong. There's 25 סלע sela to a
מנה. mana. So let's do it again. So the first position was
a מנה mana and a half for each sheep, which is 37
and a half סלע sela to each sheep. Right. Then you have,
exactly, then you have the position that a מנה mana and a
half for the, for all together, 37 and a half for all
together. Then you have שמואל Shmuel who says 60 all together, and
then you have רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan who just says six all
together. Okay, so the 60 and the six remain the same. I
just got the number wrong, it was 25 סלע sela to a
מנה. mana. So the first position that says a מנה mana and
a half for everything is 37 and a half סלע, sela, and
the
דוסא בן הרכינס Dosa ben Harkinas would be 100 and, 127, what
is it? 100, what is it? 187.5.
187.5, which equals about eight pounds.
Eight pounds. Okay, so if 187.5, let's make it easier, let's assume
200 equals eight pounds. So let's say 100 equals four pounds. So
therefore when שמואל Shmuel says 60, right, that would be about what,
a little more than two and a half pounds, something like that,
when שמואל Shmuel says 60. Okay, a little more than two pounds.
And when, and when רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan says six, that's essentially,
we said four pounds is 100, so a six, so what is
it?
A tenth of 60, so a tenth of two pounds.
A tenth of two pounds, so two-tenths of a pound. Okay, so
not much. Okay, but anyway, at least we have, and that's how
much you have to shear, right? That's how much you have to
shear, right. Okay, we have to end. At least we have our
conversion table. A מנה mana is, a, okay, so once more, the
conversion is a מנה mana is 25 סלע, sela, which is 100
דינר, dinar, and now based on Artscroll we have decided that a,
oh actually it works out well. Shh. If 100, if 100 סלע
sela is four pounds, that actually works out, here's the easier conversion.
It means a מנה mana is approximately one pound. So we'll remember
that tomorrow, that our conversion is that a מנה mana is one
pound. To be continued.